<?xml version="1.0"?>
<PropertyList>

    <name>Engine handling: Winter flying</name>

    <description>
This 5 minutes short Tutorial will tell you what to keep in mind when flying in cold weather.

You can start it anywhere, currently its just a lecture.

----------------
For additional info, please also refer to the Pilots Operating Manual (POH), page 4-32.

- Preflight check:
  - Clean any ice/snow accumulation.
  - Be sure to toroughly drain the fuel system for water contaminants.
  - Preheat the engine using the preheater before starting.
  - If temperatures are consistently below 20°F/-6°C, apply the winterization kit.

- Engine operation:
  - Priming needs a little more fuel.
  - For starting, use the external power source to relieve the battery (master switch off!).
  - Engine runs cooler, correctly lean the engine. Watch the CHT and oil temps.
  - Idle at 1000-1200 RPM and peak EGT.
  - Add a bit of throttle to avoid the engine dying shortly after starting.
  - Consider changing the oil to winter variant (for example SAE 30 grade).

- Flying:
  - Especially watch for icing conditions (humid air).
  - Consider the conditions of runways and expect longer takeoff/landing roll distances
    especially with snow covered surfaces.
    </description>
    
    <!--<init>
        <set>
            <property>/sim/model/c182s/brake-parking</property>
            <value>1</value>
        </set>
    </init>-->
    
    
    <!-- Intro -->
    <step>
        <message>In this lesson, you'll learn what to keep in mind when flying in winter or cold weather
            because cold weather will have consequences for engine operation and flight characteristics.</message>
        <wait>8</wait>
    </step>
    
    
    <!-- Preflight -->
    <step>
        <message>
            Before going to fly, you need to make sure your plane is ready for the cold weather during the preflight check.</message>
        <wait>6</wait>
    </step>
    <step>
        <message>When you approach your plane, be sure to remove all ice and snow accumulation from it. Even small
            amounts of snow will have adverse effects on your planes performance.
            You can do this by pressing the {"clean"|clean} button from the airplane options menu.</message>
        <wait>20</wait>
    </step>
    <step>
        <message>The oil in the plane is cold and thus has a high viscosity. To ensure smooth engine operation and reduce wear and tear,
            apply the Preheater to warm the oil. The time it takes depends on the temperatures.
            You can apply the preheater from the aircrafts ground equipment menu.</message>
        <wait>18</wait>
    </step>
    <step>
        <message>Also consider switching to oil that is better suited for cold temperatures, like {SAE 30|S A E thirty} grade.</message>
        <wait>10</wait>
    </step>
    <step>
        <message>When you fly in temperatures below {20 degF/-6 degC|20 degrees fahrenheit} you should equip the winterizatoin kit.
            This is some insulation inside the cowling and also a pair of metal plates blocking most of the air inlet at the nose.
            The blocked intake will reduce cooling airflow and thus result in an overall warmer engine.</message>
        <wait>25</wait>
    </step>
    
    
    <!-- Engine operation -->
    <step>
        <message>Starting the engine in cold weather is basicly the same procedure as normally.
            However, you will need to prime a little more, but don't flood the engine!</message>
        <wait>15</wait>
    </step>
    <step>
        <message>When there are freezing temperatures, you risk your spark plugs freezing over when the engine dies off
            after startup as long as it is still cold. Consider opening the throttle a little more.</message>
        <wait>15</wait>
    </step>
    <step>
        <message>Also, the battery is sensitive to cold, so you should apply the external power source.
            Cranking will drain considerable energy and in cold weather you don't want to overstress the battery.
            Toggle the master switch off and access the external power source trough the aircrafts ground equipment menu.</message>
        <wait>20</wait>
    </step>
    <step>
        <message>As long as the engine is cold, it will not develop full power. Properly warm the engine by letting it
            run at {1000-1200|thousand to thousand two hundred} RPM and a lean mixture until the oil and {CHT|cylinder head temperature}
            is in the greens. When advacing the throttle, the engine should increase RPM smoothly.</message>
        <wait>20</wait>
    </step>
    
    
    <!-- Flying -->
    <step>
        <message>Once the engine is running, keep it warm by idling with {1000-1200|thousand to thousand two hundred} RPM
            at peak {EGT|exhaust gas temperature} also for ground operations. Keep an eye to the {CHT|cylinder head} and oil temperature, especially during longer descends,
            and relean as appropriate.</message>
        <wait>20</wait>
    </step>
    <step>
        <message>For takeoffs (and landings) take notice of the runway condition. {Snow/Ice|Snow} covered surfaces
            will considerably prolong your rolling distance and braking effectiveness.
            Consider also, that you need some runway after an aborted takeoff roll. Abort early if power does
            not develop as expected, and be sure to check full throttle operation early in the takeoff run.</message>
        <wait>25</wait>
    </step>
    <step>
        <message>Once in the air, you should constantly be aware of icing conditions. Especially near the freezing point
            this can happen quickly. Very cold air is usually dry, but watch out for supercooled water vapor.</message>
        <wait>15</wait>
    </step>
    
    
    <!-- Epilog -->
    <step>
        <message>You now know how to operate the plane when its cold out there.</message>
    </step>


</PropertyList>
